Hey everyone, Trisha here. You're
watching The Plain Bagel. There's been a
lot of talk about Alberta separatism
lately. Started off as a fringe movement
that slowly picked up steam and thanks
to changes made at the provincial level
to make a referendum easier to have, the
Alberta Prosperity Project, a non-profit
pushing for independence, has started
collecting signatures to put the
question to voters as to whether Alberta
should leave the rest of Canada. And as
you can imagine in the current
environment, the whole thing has been
pretty controversial. Canada is already
facing a trade war from the United
States and threats from Trump to turn
the country into the 51st state via
economic pressure. The news broke last
month of separatist meeting with US
officials to discuss a $500 billion loan
to help the province transition to
independence, something BC Premier David
Eby likened to treason. Now right from
the get-go, it's worth highlighting
these aren't elected officials and only
a minority of Albertans, between 19 and
29% according to recent polls, actually
support independence to varying degrees,
which while high for Canada is actually
on par with some US states like
California and actually less than demand
for independence from states like Texas
and Alaska. And the Alberta Prosperity
Project behind the referendum, the most
vocal group in pushing for independence
here, is very much a a
questionable organization, we'll call
it. In their own marketing material,
which starts with a quote of the US
Declaration of Independence, the group
laments about Alberta's quote, "downhill
spiral into the vortex of the WEF UN
Marxist agenda that'll be exacerbated by
the proposed digital ID, programmable
digital currency, and the ESG credit
score to control every aspect of your
life." And there are plenty of other
examples of the group's co-founder
Jeffrey Rath and CEO Mitch Sylvester
saying pretty outlandish stuff. Yet this
fringe group has been given quite the
megaphone, especially among some within
the mega crowd. Personalities on Twitter
would have you believe that Albertans
are dead set on separating or even
joining in US, sharing videos of long
lines and filled venues for referendum
events, and Treasury Secretary Scott
Bessent has even recently commented on
working with Alberta as an independent
country. All of which, obviously, raises
anxieties about foreign interference
from an administration that would
actively benefit from a divided Canada.
Now, ultimately, Albertans have every
right to self-advocate in discussing
their relationship with the federal
government. But, the current campaign
being run by the Alberta Prosperity
Project is built on misconceptions and
misinformation. With the group making
some pretty tall promises, saying
they'll eliminate income taxes, sales
taxes, save families tens of thousands
of dollars a year, all with no grounding
in reality, and no consideration for the
substantial risks and costs of
secession. Which is why I want to cover
the topic. I know this is a political
issue, and I don't usually like to cover
the messy stuff, but I wanted to discuss
the economic aspects that are often used
to justify the idea of Albertan
independence, and really put them to
some scrutiny. Especially given the
likelihood that we might face a vote
here, and the risk of misinformation
from either Wrath or Trump influencing
people's decision. But, before hopping
into the messy stuff, let's start with a
bit of a primer
about Alberta. At the risk of sounding
like a third-grade Canadian geography
teacher, Alberta is one of Canada's
three prairie provinces, known for its
agriculture, with the province making up
nearly half of livestock and crop market
receipts, and landscapes, with the
province hosting a range of the Rocky
Mountains and Banff National Park, the
first and top-rated Canadian National
Park. It's also home to the world's
largest outdoor rodeo, the Calgary
Stampede, and the world's largest statue
of a dinosaur,
named Tyra. Now, economically speaking,
Alberta is most known for its oil and
gas industry, with the province alone
making up over 80% of the country's
total oil production in 2024, thanks
largely to its oil sands, which alone
account for 98%
of Canada's proven oil reserves. Now,
the province isn't the biggest economy
in the country. It represents about 15%
of gross domestic product compared to
Ontario at 39% and Quebec at 20%. But,
the province's resources have helped the
province consistently achieve the
highest GDP per capita and average
income among provinces. Now, as you
might expect from a province that's
sometimes called the Texas of the North,
Alberta is fairly right-leaning when it
comes to its politics. And with Canada
having been run by liberals since 2015,
this has been the source of some tension
over the past decade. Environmental
policies like the carbon tax and
burdensome approval processes for oil
projects and a general lack of support
for pipeline development from
neighboring provinces has held back
growth and investment for Alberta's oil
and gas sector. And with majority of
Canadians living in Ontario and Quebec
alone, some have argued that Canada is
experiencing Western alienation. This
idea that Eastern provinces are largely
dominating politics for the country.
Something that has contributed to this
growing separatist sentiment. Now,
Canada is no stranger to separatist
movements. In fact, the country's
predominantly French province of Quebec
has already had two referendums on
independence. The latter of which just
barely saw the province remain as a part
of Canada in 1995 with the remain vote
winning by a sliver at 50.6%
of the vote. But, compared to Quebec,
Alberta doesn't have the same deep roots
or cultural concerns around things like
language and the like. In fact, in all
of its history, Alberta has only ever
elected one separatist to its
legislative assembly. Whereas, the Bloc
Québécois, a national party dedicated to
Quebec's sovereignty that's previously
pushed heavily for separatism, was
actually the official opposition from
1993 to 1997 and even today holds a good
number of seats in the country's House
of Commons. So, then what's driving the
desire to separate now? Well, aside from
the political grievance from a largely
conservative province around a liberal
party remaining in power after a long
Justin Trudeau term. The arguments made
are largely fiscal in nature with one of
the main points being around transfer
payments. As mentioned, Albertan
households have a higher average income,
which thanks to Canada's progressive tax
system, also means they tend to pay
higher taxes. A good chunk of this taxes
goes towards transfer payments, which
are distributed among the provinces to
cover things like education, health
care, and social services. One of these
transfers, known as equalization
payments, is specifically designed to
redistribute revenue from wealthier
provinces to those with lower income to
quote, "Ensure that all Canadians have
access to broadly comparable levels of
public services." And these equalization
transfers have been a point of
frustration for the provincial
government. While the amounts don't
represent an explicit fee charged to
Alberta since all Canadians again face
the same progressive tax rates, the
province doesn't receive any amount from
the transfers, making it a net
contributor. And Alberta Premier
Danielle Smith argues that when you
consider all transfers beyond just
equalization, Alberta sends out over 20
billion dollars more annually to the
rest of Canada than it receives back in
benefits. An amount that represents an
average of around 4,000 dollars per
capita. So, there's this view that
Alberta is subsidizing other provinces
in the country and there is some truth
to that. With this view also extending
to Alberta's contribution to the Canada
Pension Plan. Much like how social
security works in the US, every employee
in Canada pays a portion of their
paycheck towards the CPP. That amount
gets matched by their employer and
invested to help grow the pot. And when
the employee retires, they're able to
receive payments from the program
depending on their age, contribution
period, and their average earnings while
they worked. Now, Alberta has a younger
than average population, meaning that
Albertans tend to make more
contributions to the program than they
see benefits redeemed. And because of
the higher average income, some believe
the province has made a disproportionate
contribution to the country's pension
plan. In fact, one 2023 LifeWorks report
estimated that based on contributions,
withdrawals, and historical performance,
the province's share of CPP sat around
$334
billion,
representing roughly half of the entire
country's plan. Now, the federal act
that created the CPP actually allows
provinces to leave with their share of
the pot to start their own provincial
pension plan. Quebec itself has been
running an independent pension plan
since the beginning. So, as you can
expect, there's been a lot of demand to
take this money and run. Now, we need to
highlight that this calculation is very
widely contested for reasons that we'll
touch on. But, the Alberta Prosperity
Project estimates that even if the
province ended up with just half of this
amount, province could achieve a fiscal
surplus of $23.6
billion
to $45.5 billion by cutting off ties
with Canada's federal government, even
after accounting for the upfront costs
and the ongoing expenses of replacing
federal functions, which compares to the
forecasted multi-billion dollar deficits
the province is expecting over the next
few years. So, you can see the appeal.
It's argued that Albertan independence
would both decrease taxes and increase
the province's budgetary surplus. And
eliminating the overhang of federal
regulations could bolster investment and
economic growth for the province. All of
which sounds pretty compelling.
Except for the fact that it's completely
unfounded. Yes, progressive taxes do
lead to Albertans paying higher taxes
since they earn, again, higher average
incomes, and that is being used to help
support other provinces in the country.
New Brunswick, for example, sees nearly
a quarter of its revenue paid for by
other provinces via equalization
transfers. But, there's a whole slew of
problems with the estimates being used
by the Alberta Prosperity Project here.
Dr. Trevor Tom, a professor of economics
and director of fiscal and economic
policy at the University of Calgary, for
example,
nice last name, by the way, has himself
pointed out a few issues with the
report, namely the cost and revenue
assumptions used to calculate these
generous figures
just don't make any sense. There are a
number of oversights in the
calculations. The group completely
forgets about old age security and the
Canada child benefit, essentially
arguing that Albertans will continue to
receive these payments without
explaining where the $10 billion to fund
these programs will ultimately come
from. The group also assumes that
Alberta could build an entire military
presence for just a few billion dollars,
even though the NATO target of 2% of GDP
would put the annual spending alone at
$10 billion a year, an amount that would
eventually rise to $25 billion under the
new phasing in of the 5% target.
Meanwhile, on the revenue side, the
group bases oil royalty estimates on an
oil price of $85 Canadian a barrel,
which at the time of the draft was
closer to accurate given that oil prices
spiked in the month the report was
released. But today, the Western
Canadian Select Benchmark, what most
Albertan producers receive for their
oil, is sitting at just $69 Canadian a
barrel. But the most bizarre issue is
that 16% of the Albertan government's
revenue under this plan, about $23
billion, or essentially the entire
fiscal surplus on the low end, appears
to come from the returns and
contributions by Albertans to the Canada
Pension Plan.
So I guess Alberta will just commandeer
pensioner income to fund its
independence. That also brings us to the
issues with that calculation of
Alberta's share of the CPP, because even
with just using half that estimate, the
assumptions being used here just aren't
realistic. In fact, if other provinces
used the same assumptions that were used
in the Lifeworks report, there wouldn't
be enough money to go around. Ontario
and Alberta alone would take up the
entire pot of money. Reason being that
the Lifeworks calculation is
oversimplified and doesn't account for
the full impact of withdrawals on
investment returns, nor are influence of
worker mobility. You see, it's very
common for Canadians from other
provinces to move and work in Alberta
when they're young, especially in the
oil and gas sector, and then retire and
receive their government benefits in a
different province, which has
contributed to Alberta having the lowest
age demographic among the provinces.
But, this can skew the numbers, making
it look like Albertans are paying for
the retirement of other Canadians,
even if that isn't really the case. So,
even the Prosperity Project's 25%
assumption is an aggressive estimate
when you consider Alberta represents
just 12% of the country's population and
16% of the CPP's contributions. So,
right away, there are some pretty
glaring issues with the fiscal utopia
that's being promised for Alberta
separation.
Then, there's the risks, downsides, and
costs that
haven't been covered here. For one,
there's the pretty obvious issue of
Alberta becoming a landlocked nation
between Canada and the US, which, aside
from the military and border
implications, also presents a pretty big
issue for trade. Alberta is already the
most US trade-dependent province in
Canada, sending the vast majority of its
oil down south. And any access to
Canada's west coast, where the province
currently sells its oil to China, would
have to go through British Columbia. So,
not only would Alberta immediately lose
access to Kuzma and the Canadian free
trade agreement with other provinces,
but it would also have to renegotiate
these trade relations from a pretty
disadvantaged position. And even without
implementing explicit tariffs, it's
likely that trade costs would increase.
As highlighted by Dr. Toom, research on
Brexit has found that non-tariff
barriers increased by 3 to 8% for the UK
after it left the EU, with estimates for
the impact on GDP ranging from 2 to 5%
for Alberta. A 5% increase in trade
costs alone could cause its economy to
lose out on an estimated $20 annually.
Secondly, there's a risk of capital and
human capital flight here. The truth is
that companies and investors don't like
political instability, nor the risk of
losing access to nearly 90% of Canada's
population. So, there's a good chance
that we see companies and employees
leave the province, thereby shrinking
the tax base and hurting economic
activity, even just on the threat of
secession. Something we actually saw
firsthand with Quebec. From 1976 to
1979, while the separatist party
Quebecois was in power, an estimated 368
businesses moved their headquarters out
of the province, with even the Bank of
Montreal moving to Toronto, Ontario.
This is also an issue given Alberta's
dependence on labor from other
provinces, especially for its oil, gas,
and construction industries. So, any
barrier on labor mobility is going to be
a meaningful headwind here. Then,
there's the question of money.
Like, actual money. What would Alberta
use as its currency if it were to
separate? The Alberta Prosperity Project
proposes that the province adopt the US
dollar
for some reason, and then eventually
transition to its own Albertan dollar
backed by gold, Bitcoin, and oil, but
doesn't account for the cost of setting
up those reserves, nor the risk of a
province that's a fraction of the
country's size,
launching a new currency from scratch.
And truly, these are just some of the
issues of the countless list of risks
and costs that just aren't being
considered here. Replacing
infrastructure for healthcare,
education, employment insurance, and
pension funding. Establishing border
patrol for a border that's now over 10
times larger than before. The
development of a new legal and court
system. The reestablishment of
international relations without access
to Canada's reputation and G7 status.
Less favorable lending terms given the
uncertainty. Alberta's share of federal
debt that the Canada government might
hitch on the province on the way out.
The issue of federally owned land. You
could kiss Banff goodbye because that's
run federally, not provincially. The
question of indigenous rights and areas,
and the need to renegotiate there. The
fact that since Quebec, Canadian law has
been updated so that it no longer allows
unilateral secession, meaning a yes
referendum vote may not even lead to
independence. And of course, the issue
of 25% of the province's GDP coming from
oil and gas, an incredibly volatile
industry to base your economy off of. A
big selling point for independence here
is the idea that Alberta could
deregulate and double down on its oil
and gas sector to bolster economic
activity. But oil can be pretty
unreliable. The Albertan government's
revenues from oil and gas have
fluctuated from as low as 6.5% of their
total income to as high as 33.2%
in just the past decade alone. In fact,
the Alberta government is currently
bracing for higher deficits due to
currently low oil prices. And we've seen
the province struggle during oil gluts
in the past. So while oil has
historically been a great boon for the
Albertan government, that might not
always be the case. And one of the
benefits of remaining as part of Canada
is the industrial diversification it
provides should things turn sour.
Ontario, for example, has fluctuated
between being a net contributor and a
net recipient of equalization payments.
And while it's true that Alberta has not
received an equalization transfer since
the 1960s, it may not always be able to
rely on its above-average GDP per capita
and young demographics. Now, there are
certainly valid criticisms of federal
policies and how they are impacting
Alberta.
I mean, this is Canada we're talking
about. We have a reputation of of
holding back our industries with red
tape. But Alberta doesn't operate in a
closed system, so it's actually quite
difficult to accurately estimate many of
these figures, to quantify its
relationship with the rest of Canada
when you consider things like labor
mobility, military spending, and the
federal tax credits and supports given
to oil and gas companies that pay for
Alberta's royalties. But what is almost
certain is that secession would prove
incredibly challenging for the province
of Alberta. And it's very likely that it
would cost more than it would save.
Canada itself, of course, would suffer
as well. Alberta is a very important
economy and should be recognized for its
contribution to the country. But
independence could prove fiscally
devastating for Alberta. Some may
believe it's so worth it. We're really
just talking about the economic
considerations here.
But a vote shouldn't be held under false
pretenses. In 2016, there was a lot of
misinformation and confusion about
Brexit when just over 50% of voters
chose to leave the European Union. In
2025, 5 years after officially leaving,
polls suggest that the majority of
respondents ultimately believe it was
the wrong decision. Now, as mentioned,
Albertan separatists do currently remain
a minority in the province. And there is
a good chance that the provincial
government is using the movement as a
bargaining chip in its relations with
the federal government. Premier Danielle
Smith has done things like reducing the
number of signatures needed to put the
referendum to a vote, while also talking
about a united Canada. But with the
onslaught of misinformation coming our
way and likely to come our way in the
future, especially if we approach an
actual referendum vote,
hopefully this video helped to clear the
air. Thanks for watching. Hopefully you
found this video helpful. If you did,
please do make sure to like, subscribe,
all that good stuff. It does help the
channel tremendously.
Let me know your thoughts on Alberta
separatism, whether there are any points
that you think were missed. Is it
something you're strongly supportive of?
Are you vehemently against it? Any and
all thoughts welcome in the comments
down below. Thanks again for joining me
and as always,
peace out there.